# **PEDRO RODRIGUEZ** DATA ANALYST

Stanford, CA pjrodriguez.mercado@gmail.com (787) 237-9322

m www.linkedin.com/in/pedro-rodriguez-mercado

## SUMMARY

Industrial engineer with 3+ years of experience analyzing data to develop business strategies and improve process efficiency. Proficient knowledge in data wrangling, data storytelling, data visualization, and exploratory data analysis using Python, SQL, and Tableau. Currently seeking a position as a data analyst to provide meaningful business insight and support decision-making processes.

# **SKILLS**

LANGUAGES: Python (Pandas, NumPy, Scikit-Learn), SQL DATA COLLECTION: JSON, CSV, API, Web-Scraping DATA VISUALIZATION: MatplotLib, Seaborn, Plotly, Tableau

ENGINEERING: Lean Six Sigma, Statistical Quality Control, Process Optimization, Critical Thinking, Problem-solving, Structural analysis

MACHINE LEARNING: Hypothesis Testing, A/B Testing, Linear Regression, Logistic Regression, Classification, kNN, Random

Forest, Naive Bayes, K-Means Clustering

# **PROJECTS**

## SPRINGBOARD-PRODUCTION LINE SIMULATION PROJECT

Nov. 2020 to Feb. 2021

- Performed exploratory data analysis (EDA) to identify trends in the production line and factors that might affect production goals.
- Created a simulation using SimPy to visualize how possible solutions can improve the production output by 8%.

#### **BOSTON SCIENTIFIC- CAPSTONE PROJECT**

Aug. 2016 to Mar. 2016

- Applied statistical quality control to assess the behavior of annual demand and employed layout improvements to increase production.
- Identify solutions to increase production efficiency by 20% and space optimization by 40% using the 5S and Kaizen methodology.

#### **EMPLOYMENT**

**BOSTON SCIENTIFIC** 

Dorado, PR

Industrial Engineer

Sept. 2018 to Dec. 2018

- Designed a data collection plan and performed a time study to evaluate the production line performance and determine how many employees are needed to meet the daily production demand.
- · Conducted a data-driven root-cause analysis to identify the cause of downtime events and developed standardized operation procedures.
- · Communicated project status and results to production line works, engineers, and company executives.

**MEDTRONIC** Cataño, PR

Associate Quality Engineer

June 2018 to Sept. 2018

- · Performed activities related to creating reports, change controls, and audits for warehouse re-localization.
- Ensured that corrective measures met acceptable reliability standards and that documentation was compliant with requirements.
- · Modified, applied, and maintain Data quality standards and protocol for processing materials into partially finished or finished materials product.

## **BUSINESS IMPROVEMENT & MARKETING SOLUTION**

San Juan, PR

Consultant Engineer

May 2017 to June 2018

- Trained 500+ government and public workers on how to fill the forms.
- Collected and analyzed more than 30,000 data to identify variance, service needs, and human resources for the restructuration of the PR Family department.
- · Provided data insights into basic improvement methodology and tools to the Puerto Rico Family Department.
- Designed a proposal to improve space utilization by 41% projecting a 1 million USD reduction per year.
- Collaborated with the IT department by identifying, collecting, and creating a Dashboard of the critical measures and performance metric targets.

#### **AWARDS**

## **QUEST COMPETITION - First Place winner**

May 2016

- Developed strategies and provided recommendations to improve process flow and reduce delays.
- Performed a time study analysis and used statistics and quality tools to determine the possible causes of medical devices' manufacturing

#### **EDUCATION**

#### **Polytechnic University of Puerto Rico**

2011-2017

B.S. Industrial Engineering

## **Springboard Data Science Certification**

2020-2021

- 500+ hours of hands-on course material, with 1:1 industry expert mentor oversight and completion of 2 in-depth portfolio projects.
- Mastered skills in Python, SQL, data wrangling, data visualization, hypothesis testing, and machine learning.